<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Here Be Dragons</title><link href="https://msvalina.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://msvalina.org/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://msvalina.org/</id><updated>2024-08-04T10:30:24+02:00</updated><subtitle>Thoughts on navigating at the edge of order and chaos. Seriously. And some IT stuff.</subtitle><entry><title>Reflections and lessons from failed React workout app</title><link href="https://msvalina.org/2019/10/reflections-and-lessons-from-failed-react-workout-app.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-25T10:49:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-04T10:30:24+02:00</updated><author><name>marijan</name></author><id>tag:msvalina.org,2019-10-25:/2019/10/reflections-and-lessons-from-failed-react-workout-app.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This story is about failed personal project I took between jobs. &lt;strong&gt;How
microscopic end result I have to show. But still got something valuable, or
not, you be the judge.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update 25 Mar 2020. In the mean time I did &amp;quot;finish&amp;quot; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/msvalina/jun-a-k"&gt;React Django GraphQL app&lt;/a&gt; for
reporting wild dumps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="background"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background …&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This story is about failed personal project I took between jobs. &lt;strong&gt;How
microscopic end result I have to show. But still got something valuable, or
not, you be the judge.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update 25 Mar 2020. In the mean time I did &amp;quot;finish&amp;quot; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/msvalina/jun-a-k"&gt;React Django GraphQL app&lt;/a&gt; for
reporting wild dumps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="background"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's fall of 2015. Four years ago. I quit my job as Magento backend
developer. It lasted only three months... Preparation for position took
learning PHP for a year, and some months. On mornings before daily
programing job. But that is a different story. So I need a new job, but I
don't have to rush it. I'm thinking to myself. Let's build simple workout app
for exercise routine I'm doing. Let's build it with some new technology that
will help me land a new job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="app-and-technology"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;App and technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Workout routine for app is from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.startbodyweight.com/2014/01/basic-routine-infographic-poster.html"&gt;StartBodyweight.com&lt;/a&gt;, it's simple and
good for beginners starting bodyweight exercises. It's based on this infographic poster.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.startbodyweight.com/2014/01/basic-routine-infographic-poster.html"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Start bodyweight poster" class="align-center" src="https://msvalina.org/assets/images/startbodyweight-com-poster.jpg" style="width: 75%;" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web is not going anywhere. JavaScript is not going anywhere. I should orient
toward them, is my thought stream. It's new beginning and I'm choosing
to learn new — as some would describe — revolutionary technology. It's
React — A JavaScript library for building user interfaces — invented at
Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is with paradigm shifts, new tech, best practices are not
established for some time after invention. And in React case from start it is
explicitly minimal in nature. Also, Facebook did not lead the way at the time
with supporting frameworks, tools, and practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That left a lot of space for enthusiast developers to fill the gaps needed to
make complete application with React. &lt;strong&gt;Explosion of boilerplates code
happened.&lt;/strong&gt; Small frameworks that provide scaffolding code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many questions in front of me. Can I build something useful only
with React? Which boilerplate to choose? Should I build only client side
application? Why not build backend in JS also? I should go with express,
right? How good is that MongoDB that everyone is talking about? Why not use
JSON Web Token for authentication? Why not use Server Side Rendering to speed
up loading time? What about latest ECMA script standard? Of course I should
use webpack, right? And so on...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions lead me to try and experiment with different approaches.
A lot of research, and not so much development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="result"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent two and a half months on project. On backend side, we can say that
minimal viable product, working API is done. It support users, authentication,
progressions, progression entries, and workout sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the design side. What I have to show are this half baked wireframes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Start bodyweight app wireframes" class="align-center" src="https://msvalina.org/assets/images/sbw-wireframe.jpg" style="width: 95%;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And from frontend there is almost nothing. I tried to use, many different boilerplates.
Started with simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;react + webpack + babel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kriasoft/react-starter-kit/compare/v0.4.0...v0.4.1"&gt;react + react-router + react-hot-loader&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then figured I wanted state management. I tried three different redux
implementations, with all latest bells and whistles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/bdefore/universal-redux-jwt"&gt;universal-redux-jwt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/joshgeller/react-redux-jwt-auth-example"&gt;react-redux-jwt-auth-example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/erikras/react-redux-universal-hot-example"&gt;react-redux-universal-hot-example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that in the end I would settle on react-redux-universal-hot-example.
And my time expired because I got new job offer. Which I took.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mistakes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mistakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did I do so little?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of story can be describe as distraction...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Distracted boyfriend meme looking at new boilerplate" class="align-center" src="https://msvalina.org/assets/images/boilerplate-distracion.jpg" style="width: 80%;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the plan was to do everything by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that is also part of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I have time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had time, just not as much as I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ever present problem of estimation in software development...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to use every possible cutting edge technology at the time...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="leesons"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Leesons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New technology and fast results are not good combination.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to underestimate complexity of simple applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&amp;amp;D is not development.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimum viable product. Repeat MVP, MVP, MVP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="on-javascript-fatigue"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;On JavaScript fatigue&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many before me have identified this phenomenon as &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.quora.com/Why-is-Javascript-Framework-fatigue-considered-a-big-problem"&gt;JavaScript fatigue&lt;/a&gt;. I
would not say this is that big of problem. Yes it would be easier if there
were standards, best practices and less choices.
But bigger problem in my case is that &lt;strong&gt;I was learning too many things at
once.&lt;/strong&gt; I'm not seasoned JavaScript developer. That meant, a lot of catching
up, and a lot of unsuccessful pitfall avoidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-did-i-get-from-all-this-boilerplates"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What did I get from all this boilerplates?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well I did actually bother to understand every boilerplate that I used. I did
my homework on understanding nodejs, express, mongoose, babel, on the backend side.
And on frontend side react, webpack, SSR, babel, redux. My head was not in the sand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's blast from the past. My broken truth with reflections. A way to draw
leassons from failed project. Showcase of my current abilities. Failed
showcase, but still. It should at least shed some light at my skill as
Frontend DevOps Engineer, or as failed Full Stack Developer. Thank you for
reading. Have a nice day. 💗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="freelancing"></category><category term="skills"></category><category term="frontend"></category><category term="react"></category></entry><entry><title>Role of tools and environment in behavior, and why I switched to Ubuntu/VSCode from Arch/VIM after 8 years</title><link href="https://msvalina.org/2019/09/role-of-tools-and-environment-in-behavior-and-why-i-switched-to-ubuntu-vscode-from-arch-vim.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-26T10:49:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-21T12:04:00+02:00</updated><author><name>marijan</name></author><id>tag:msvalina.org,2019-09-26:/2019/09/role-of-tools-and-environment-in-behavior-and-why-i-switched-to-ubuntu-vscode-from-arch-vim.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="takeaway"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaway&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With better tools in your environment your ability will be higher. This will
lead to doing more which will in turn give you more actual skills. Then
it will be easier to do that behaviors in future even without tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a story about role of environment in …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="takeaway"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaway&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With better tools in your environment your ability will be higher. This will
lead to doing more which will in turn give you more actual skills. Then
it will be easier to do that behaviors in future even without tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a story about role of environment in our behavior. It's written
through my personal journey. Lot of it can be &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lesspenguiny.com/articles/best-article-on-bragging"&gt;looked like and probably is
bragging&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;Hope is though, that you will get some useful info out of it.&lt;/strong&gt;
For regular people -- not geeks -- to understand this article here are crude
descriptions of tools used. They are all free and open source technologies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ubuntu: Linux Operating System (OS) for PCs built for regular people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VSCode: text editor with very easy learning curve and many great extensions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arch Linux: Linux OS for die hard geeks with hard learning curve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VIM: text editor for die hard geeks with hard learning curve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img alt="VIM inside VSCode" class="align-center" src="https://msvalina.org/assets/images/vim-in-vscode.png" style="width: 85%;" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="accidental-success"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accidental success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's year 2009, it's third semester at my University journey. I'm more happy
about running Ubuntu then learning. Around that time friend of mine suggests
and helps me install Arch Linux OS. It's the coolest operating system for
wannabe hacker at the time. Cool thing about it is that you have to construct
it by yourself. Like Lego's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was huge change. Until that moment my knowledge about Linux like
OS was more theoretical then practical. That started to change
because everything I wanted and needed for my assignments I
had to setup by my self. That meant a lot of tries and errors, and getting
hands dirty to actually understand the underlying technologies and concepts.
That process is and was very painful and frustrating at times. &lt;strong&gt;But I had no
fallback computer&lt;/strong&gt;. I gave away my laptop to parents. More accidentally
though, then purposely to change environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="My small room with PC, laptop and a bed." class="align-center" src="https://msvalina.org/assets/images/university-apartment.jpg" style="width: 85%;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Success was sticking with Arch for first year. That only happened because
there were no fallback&lt;/strong&gt;. After that my skills were much better and sticking
with all the housekeeping that needs to be done when running Arch was not a
big deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On journey of 8 years with Arch I got a lot of good stuff. Most importantly
skills and knowledge about tools, concepts and ecosystem of applications in
general. But also insights about different Free and Open Source Software --
FOSS -- community cultures and benevolent dictators. On the bad side, I
formed some half baked opinions and values. Mostly held dogmatically as would
describe well my personal development at that time. Which can be summarized
as: open source is the only way to go. I was missing that &lt;strong&gt;these are just
means in bigger fight for values in this universe.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="analysis-of-behaviors-tools-skills-and-environment"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analysis of behaviors, tools, skills and environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before returning to values. Let's see how can we understand our behavior. For
that we need a model. Best model out there is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.behaviormodel.org/"&gt;Fogg Behavior Model&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;FBM&lt;/strong&gt;. FBM
says &lt;strong&gt;Behavior&lt;/strong&gt; happens when &lt;strong&gt;Motivation&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Ability&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Prompt&lt;/strong&gt;
come at &lt;strong&gt;the same time&lt;/strong&gt;. Prompt says do the thing now! There is connection
between Motivation and Ability which is &lt;strong&gt;Action Line&lt;/strong&gt;. If combination of
Motivation and Ability is bellow Action Line when Prompt happens there will
be no Behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://www.behaviormodel.org/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Meme - Well... thank you captain obvious" class="align-center" src="https://msvalina.org/assets/images/fogg-behavior-model-graphic-2019.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's take for example donating to your favorite charity. If somebody asks you
to donate 1000$, and you don't have that money with you or it is too much for
you. Your Ability will be very low and if you don't have huge Motivation you
wont do that Behavior. But if they ask for 10$ and you want to do it, and you
have the money with you, Behavior will happen. The takeaway here is that
Motivation is like a wave. It comes and goes, everybody knows that. But where
great idea is, is that &lt;strong&gt;by making things simpler or more easy to do we
don't have to rely on Motivation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="simplicity-changes-behavior"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Simplicity changes Behavior&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or in other words anything which will boost your abilities will change your
behaviors. So how can we increase our abilities you ask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by training person so that his skill increases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by simplifying action with starter step or with tiny version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by &lt;strong&gt;putting a tool or resource in person's environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="tools-are-important"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tools are important&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img alt="Meme - Well... thank you captain obvious" class="align-center" src="https://msvalina.org/assets/images/thank-you-captain-obvious.png" style="width: 85%;" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="more-important-then-you-think"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More important then you think&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With better tools or resources in your environment or context your ability
will be higher. This will lead to doing more which will in turn give you more
actual skills. Then it will be easier to do that behaviors in future even
without tools. And in different environments.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is the reason why I'm very deliberate about everything in my environment.
And why I switched Arch Linux for Ubuntu. And VIM for VSCode. And why I
bought three different chairs, and a standing desk, and so on. I'm sure that
the benefits of having more stable OS and text editor with such an easy
learning curve, great user experiences, and powerful extensions will
increase my skills even more. As they already did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ideas about behavior design comes from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.bjfogg.com"&gt;Stanford professor
BJ Fogg&lt;/a&gt;. This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tinyhabits.com"&gt;tiny part of BJ's work&lt;/a&gt; go and learn everything about it
will change your life forever! &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tinyhabits.com/book"&gt;Preorder his book on Tiny Habits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://www.tinyhabits.com/book"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Tiny Habits book cover photo" class="align-center" src="https://msvalina.org/assets/images/tiny-habits-book.webp" style="width: 75%;" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BJ's ideas did change my life. Because as most of us I also knew what would be
and what is good for me. But the problem was how to change habits. How to
change childhood conditioning. How to change lifestyle, how to make healthy
habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switching to VSCode and Ubuntu is my way to sharpen my tools. To heighten my
abilities by changing environment. So I can work more successfully on things
that I value. Hope is that you also see the arguments for importance of tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all of us, this is a call to action. We should collectively
always be aware how our our environment steers our behavior and focus on
consciously designing it. So we don't have to be saints to do the right
thing. Live long and prosper. Thank you. Have a nice day. 💗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modification notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friends rightly noted that I was jamming too much of my interest in one
article. Thank you guys for honest criticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019 Oct 19&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove parts about personal trauma, and behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019 Oct 21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove parts about Bitcoin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="tools"></category><category term="behavior"></category><category term="environment"></category></entry><entry><title>How to patch with Bitcoin, build and deploy GnuCash in Docker on Ubuntu PPA</title><link href="https://msvalina.org/2019/09/patch-with-btc-build-and-deploy-gnucash-in-docker-on-ubuntu-ppa.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-08T10:45:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-04T10:30:24+02:00</updated><author><name>marijan</name></author><id>tag:msvalina.org,2019-09-08:/2019/09/patch-with-btc-build-and-deploy-gnucash-in-docker-on-ubuntu-ppa.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Main goal of this article is to document high level steps. Steps
to patch, build, and deploy &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.gnucash.org/"&gt;GnuCash&lt;/a&gt; on Ubuntu PPA (Personal Package
Archive). Targeted audience is mid-level technical people. Also others who
want to learn more about package building, Docker practices, and Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker builds the image. GPG (Gnu …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Main goal of this article is to document high level steps. Steps
to patch, build, and deploy &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.gnucash.org/"&gt;GnuCash&lt;/a&gt; on Ubuntu PPA (Personal Package
Archive). Targeted audience is mid-level technical people. Also others who
want to learn more about package building, Docker practices, and Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker builds the image. GPG (Gnu Privacy Guard) signs package. dput
publishes packages on Ubuntu PPA. From GnuCash perspective added value is
finding all the puzzles pieces. At the end I will compare
this build process with Archlinux pkgbuild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="motivation-and-background"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation and background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gnucash.1415818.n4.nabble.com/Cryptocurrencies-td4690814.html"&gt;no official Bitcoin support&lt;/a&gt; in GnuCash. It seems like there
won't be one in future from GnuCash developers. On Archlinux I'm using
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/gnucash-xbt/"&gt;gnucash-xbt from AUR&lt;/a&gt;. On my other Ubuntu machine I wanted to use the same.
There was no PPA with Bitcoin support in GnuCash. So I created &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~msvalina/+archive/ubuntu/gnucash"&gt;Ubuntu PPA&lt;/a&gt;
for myself and others. This wasn't my first build of debian like package.
In past I hacked a Makefile to generate opkg package for OpenWRT. It was
useful knowledge to have for this task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="where-is-the-code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where is the code?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/msvalina/ppa-gnucash-xbt"&gt;code on github repo&lt;/a&gt; and skip over this article. You can
find &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~msvalina/+archive/ubuntu/gnucash"&gt;Ubuntu PPA packages&lt;/a&gt; and install them right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-puzzle-pieces-did-you-use"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What puzzle pieces did you use?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks goes to all this work before mine. It was much easier to solve all the
problems because of these people 💗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Benedykt Przybyło (b3niup) for original Archlinux AUR pkgbuild
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/gnucash-xbt/"&gt;gnucash-xbt&lt;/a&gt; and xbt.patch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dmitry Smirnov for maintaining &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/debian/gnucash/"&gt;Debian GnuCash dpkgbuild&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dale Phurrough for nice GnuCash Dockerfile starting point
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/diablodale/gnucash-dev-docker/"&gt;diablodale/gnucash-dev-docker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sicklylife for maintaining &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~sicklylife/+archive/ubuntu/gnucash3.6"&gt;vanilla GnuCash Ubuntu PPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrey Arapov of nixaid.com for writing: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nixaid.com/using-gpg-inside-a-docker-container/"&gt;Using GPG inside a docker
container&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-prerequisites-understanding-is-necessary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What prerequisites understanding is necessary?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://packaging.ubuntu.com/html/index.html"&gt;Ubuntu Packaging Guide&lt;/a&gt; is good starting point, has many useful
information. Guide also depends on debian packaging policies and tools. It is
&lt;strong&gt;important&lt;/strong&gt; to know that there are many ways/tools to build debian package.
But two main categories are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="upstream-developer-way"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Upstream Developer way&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://jameswestby.net/bzr/builddeb/user_manual/"&gt;building using bzr-build&lt;/a&gt; Ubuntu Packaging Guide focuses on this one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wiki.debian.org/PackagingWithGit"&gt;building using git-buildpackage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="debian-packager-way"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Debian packager way&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/1087569/deploying-own-debian-package-to-launchpad"&gt;Quoting from askubuntu&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
&amp;gt; In the normal workflow, packager starts by
&amp;gt; downloading *.orig.tar.gz archive then
&amp;gt; extracting.
&amp;gt;
&amp;gt;    Debian packages can be split into two kinds:
&amp;gt;    -  native '3.0 (native)' and
&amp;gt;    -  non-native '3.0 (quilt)'.
&amp;gt;    They have a slight different way in building.
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wiki.debian.org/DebianMentorsFaq#What_is_the_difference_between_a_native_Debian_package_and_a_non-native_package.3F"&gt;DebianMentorsFaq&lt;/a&gt; for difference between native and non-native.
This project uses Debian packager way with non-native(quilt) type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="why-would-you-build-inside-docker"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why would you build inside Docker?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure as Code principle is valuable and something Docker forces you
to do. Also I don't want to clutter mine laptop with build dependencies.
There are other ways to do that but, I also wanted to gather
some more experiences with Docker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="main-procedures"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Main procedures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker image will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;build the environment for building GnuCash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;patch GnuCash with Bitcoin currency type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;build debian source package&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sign it with gpg (works with YubiKey)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upload it to the Ubuntu PPA (Personal Package Archive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="interesting-parts-dockerfile"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interesting parts: Dockerfile&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First job of docker is to install all needed dependencies for build tools and
for GnuCash itself. Other interesting thing is headache less permissions with
docker volume. For that we create user and group in Dockerfile. They will
have the same UID and GID as user which is building the container&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;RUN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;groupadd&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--system&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;--gid&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;GID&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;ubuntu

&lt;span class="k"&gt;RUN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;useradd&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--system&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;--create-home&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;--home-dir&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/home/ubuntu&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;--shell&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/bin/bash&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;--uid&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;UID&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;--gid&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;GID&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;--groups&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;sudo&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;--password&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;openssl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;passwd&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-1&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ubuntu&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;ubuntu

&lt;span class="k"&gt;USER&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;ubuntu&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;WORKDIR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;/home/ubuntu/ppa-gnucash-xbt&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;CMD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;./build.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we create docker container with volumes from user that created docker
image&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;run&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--rm&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--tty&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--interactive&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;--volume&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;HOME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;/.gnupg/:/home/ubuntu/.gnupg/:ro&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;--volume&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/run/user/&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;id&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-u&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;/:/run/user/&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;id&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-u&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;/:ro&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;--volume&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;HOME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;/path/to/ppa-gnucash-xbt/:/home/ubuntu/ppa-gnucash-xbt/&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;--name&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;dpkg-build-gnucash&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;gnucash-xbt-ubuntu-bionic-pkgbuild&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;bash
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now data from repo is available both on host and container. Nobody will mess
up owner, group or permissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-happens-on-new-upstream-release"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What happens on new upstream release?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On new upstream release build.sh needs change. Latest upstream source url,
sha256 checksum of that source need modification. Other steps are automatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="interesting-parts-build-sh-script"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interesting parts: build.sh script&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In current form build.sh only builds debian source package. It doesn't
compile GnuCash itself. To build it for local use and testing run container
with bash and issue after running build.sh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ppa_builddir
dpkg-buildpackage&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--build&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;binary
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-long-will-i-maintain-ppa"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How long will I maintain PPA?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will maintain it as long as I use GnuCash. I used it for last 5
years. So if we go by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect"&gt;Lindy Effect&lt;/a&gt; I will maintain it for 5 more years.
But beware I'm looking at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hledger.org/"&gt;HLedger&lt;/a&gt; as a replacement.
Feel free to take over maintaining when PPA becomes out of date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So looking back and seeing how much time it would take me to patch and build
GnuCash for Ubuntu I can say that my intuition was completely off... It took
me 5 times more time then I anticipated. Comparing that to building on
Archlinux's, it is complex. But I get way there is so many tools and
policies in Ubuntu/Debian world. History and compatibility need preservation.
But it takes a while to get gist of things. Also Docker and GPG issues took
time as well. Hand in hand it is valuable experience for me, especially
because Ubuntu Bionic is my main OS now. For a junior level Linux guy, if
such category can be defined at all. It is real pain to build, patch and
deploy dpkg package. If you are still reading. Thank you. Hope you got
something out of it. 💗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="programming"></category><category term="bitcoin"></category><category term="gnucash"></category><category term="ubuntu"></category><category term="linux"></category><category term="docker"></category></entry></feed>